Preliminary Guide to the Don Roy Papers, 1921 - 1980
Duke University. University Archives
Don Roy papers 1921 - 1980
Roy, Donald F.
25.5 linear feet Extent: 25500 Items
Duke University. University Archives
Donald Francis Roy (1909-1980), noted industrial sociologist, was a faculty member at Duke University in the Department of Sociology from 1950 until his retirement in 1979. Roy's areas of specialization were field methods of sociological research and social conflict. The collection includes correspondence, clippings, articles, reviews, manuscripts, research and field notes, reprints, newsletters, photographs, teaching materials, pamphlets, and other written materials. The major subjects of the collection are Roy's study of industrial sociology; workplace interactions; and specific collective bargaining and union campaigns of the Textile Workers Union of America, the Teamsters Union, and the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees. English.
UA.29.02.0066
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Don Roy Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1982 (A82-44) and in 1983 (A83-106).
Biographical Note
Donald Francis Roy (1909-1980), noted industrial sociologist, was a faculty member at Duke University in the Department of Sociology from 1950 until his retirement in 1979. Roy was educated at the University of Washington (A.B., 1935; M.A., 1935) and at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1952). Roy held a number of teaching positions before he came to Duke. He taught at the University of Washington (1935-1937), the University of Oregon (1937-1938), the University of Chicago (1947-1950), Roosevelt College (1948-1950), and the Illinois Institute of Technology (1949-1950).
Roy's areas of specialization were field methods of sociological research and social conflict. Roy applied the participant observer approach to factory situations. He began in 1934 with a study of the makeshift world of unemployed men in a Seattle shantytown called Hooverville. Roy moved into Hooverville and wrote a master's thesis titled Hooverville, a Study of a Community of Homeless Men in Seattle. Roy's interest in workplace interactions led him to employment in twenty-one different occupations in twenty industries. Roy used his personal involvement in these industries as a basis for his sociological research.
Donald Roy coined the term banana time, a concept that signifies how employees have made workplaces more tolerable by participating in off-task camaraderie. Banana time refers to the collectively determined break time of factory workers, the start of which was signaled with a lunch box banana.
Roy was married and had two children.
Collection Overview
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, articles, reviews, manuscripts, research and field notes, reprints, newsletters, photographs, teaching materials, pamphlets, and other written materials. The major subjects of the collection are Roy's study of industrial sociology; workplace interactions; and specific collective bargaining and union campaigns of the Textile Workers Union of America, the Teamsters Union, and the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees.
While at Duke, Roy studied the attempts made by the Textile Workers Union of America to have union contracts accepted in some of the mills of Virginia and North Carolina. Between 1956-1959 and 1973-1979, Roy made detailed observations on the campaigns at the Hanes Knitting Company in Winston-Salem, N.C., 1956-1957; Elkin, N.C., 1956-1957; Chatham, Va., 1956; Burlington, N.C., 1957; Roanoke, Va., 1956 and 1965; Radford, Va., 1957; Vinton, Va., 1957; Dublin, Va., 1957; Altavista, Va., 1957; Henderson, N.C., 1958-1959; Roanoke Rapids, N.C., 1964-1979; Wallace, N.C., 1974 and 1977; Laurinburg, N.C., 1977-1979. The bulk of the information about these campaigns can be found in Boxes 1-5 and Boxes 14-19. Manuscripts on the Sheffield and Tyndall campaigns can be found in Box 1.
In addition, Roy followed the disputes involving the Teamsters Union in Atlanta, Ga., 1966, and the attempt by Local 77 of the American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees to establish a union at Duke Hospital in the 1960s and 1970s. Throughout his life, Roy took detailed field notes, collected materials, and retained correspondence about his industrial studies. These materials are scattered throughout the collection.
In 1965-1966, Roy spent a year on sabbatical at Cornell University. During that year, Roy wrote case studies on the Tyndall Garment Co., the Sheffield and Laurel Campaigns, the Burlington Campaign, the Corinth Study, and the Labor Organizing Campaign. Roy's field notes and observations are included in the collection.
Roy used pseudonyms, to protect confidentiality, for the names of the people and places he studied. Box 14 contains a list of the pseudonyms Roy used in his case studies. The following list gives the actual name followed by the pseudonym used by Roy in some of his studies and in his folder titles.
Hanes Knitting
Tyndall Garments
Winston-Salem, N.C.
Lancaster
Elkin, N.C.
Laurel
Chatham, Va.
Sheffield
Burlington, N.C.
Jefferson
Roanoke, Va.
Statesboro
Radford, Va.
Zebulon
Vinton, Va.
Corinth
Dublin, Va.
Indian Hills
Altavista, Va.
Cartersville
Roanoke Rapids, N.C.
Clearwater
Box 6 contains files for a book begun by Roy about his interest and involvement in union organizing. The book was not completed. The collection file contains Mrs. Roy's outline of the book's organization.
The collection file includes a paper by Huw Beynon with notes and comments about Roy's papers. Beynon's manuscript offers a proposed classification for the collection and outlines themes of Roy's work. The collection file also includes a biographical sketch by Dr. Joy K. Roy, Roy's second wife.
Subject Headings
AFSCME; Collective bargaining; Duke University. Medical Center -- Employees -- History; Duke University. Dept. of Sociology; Duke University. Dept. of Sociology -- Faculty; Duke University -- Faculty; International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; Labor unions; Labor unions -- Organizing; Labor unions -- United States; Roy, Donald F.; Social conflict; Sociology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Textile Workers Union of America -- History; Textile industry -- North Carolina; Textile industry -- Virginia; Textile workers -- Labor unions; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- North Carolina; Textile workers -- North Carolina; Textile workers -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; Clippings; Newsletters; Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Manuscripts (Box 1)
    - Sheffield (Box 1)
      Contains manuscript about the union campaign in Chatham, Va.
    - Tyndall (Box 1)
      Contains manuscript about the Hanes Knitting union campaign in Winston-Salem, N.C.
  - Union Campaigns, 1958-[1968] (Box 2)
    - Henderson, N.C., 1958-1961 (Box 2)
      Includes mostly printed matter from Locals 578 and 584 of the Textile Workers Union of America.
    - Cone, 1958-1961 (Box 2)
    - Anacostia, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Clinch Valley Coal 1967-[1968] (Box 2)
    - Elkin, 1967 (Box 2)
    - [Erwin Mills?], [1966-1967] (Box 2)
    - Whiteville, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Textile Workers Union of America Publications (Box 3)
    - Trade Worker (Box 3)
    - Textile Worker (Box 3)
    - Labor Unity (Box 3)
    - Textile Labor (Box 3)
  - Textile Workers Union of America and Elkin, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Bill Swift, Unemployment Compensation Hearings (Elkin), 1957 (Box 4)
  - Union Campaigns and Conferences, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Charlotte Conference, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Winston-Salem, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Hanes and Elkin, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Charlotte, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Roanoke and Lynchburg, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Roanoke Follow-up, Oct. 1957 (Box 4)
    - Chatham Defeat, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Radford, 1957 (Box 4)
    - Burlington Mills, 1957 (Box 4)
      Includes Vinton, Radford, Dublin, and Altavista.
    - Burlington Mills, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Vinton, 1957-1958 (Box 5)
    - Charlotte, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Winston-Salem, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Restaurant Study, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Teamsters, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Roanoke, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Marion, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Writings (Box 6)
    - The Campaign Book (Box 6)
      Contains files for a book begun by Roy about his interest and involvement in union organizing. The book was not completed. The collection file contains Mrs. Roy's outline of the book's organization.
    - Articles and Reviews (Box 7)
      Includes Banana Time field notes; a copy of The Homeless Man in Seattle; and other writings. Roy's Banana Time paper describes the social interaction that took place within a group of factory machine operators.
    - Research Notes (Box 7)
      Includes questionnaires; one notebook with field notes made during a trip to Manchester, England, to study a strike, in 1973; and other materials.
  - Duke Unions, ca. 1966-1979 (Box 8)
    Contains files primarily about Union Local #77. Also includes one folder on the Vigil, notes from April-July 1968, and folders about the Duke University Hospital.
  - Reprints and Photocopies (Box 9)
    Material in this box is from published sources.
  - Clippings (Box 10)
    Material in this box is from U.S. and foreign newspapers.
  - Collected Writings (Box 11)
    Includes writings collected by Roy. Some material is from unidentified sources.
  - Correspondence (Box 12)
  - Writings (Box 12)
    - Articles and Reviews (Box 12)
    - Manuscripts (Box 12)
    - Research Notes (Box 12)
    - Speeches (Box 12)
  - Correspondence (Box 13)
  - University of Chicago (Box 13)
  - Sociology Dept. Business (Box 13)
  - ADPi (Box 13)
  - Music (Box 13)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 13)
    Includes letters of condolence to Mrs. Roy, 1980.
  - Family Photographs (Box 13)
  - Biographical Information (Box 13)
  - Duke Teaching Materials (Box 13)
  - The Dolls (Box 13)
    Includes clippings, letters, and photographs about individuals who were Roy's undergraduates and wrote about the medical school for one of Roy's classes.
  - Cambridge University Teaching Materials, 1972-1973 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 13)
  - Union Campaigns, 1945-1978 (Box 14)
    - Cone, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Cannon, ca. 1975 (Box 14)
    - Stevens, 1965-ca. 1979 (Box 14)
    - Standard Oil, 1945-1946 (Box 14)
    - National Union of Public Employees (U.K.), 1973 (Box 14)
  - Human Nature (Box 14)
    Includes course notes from a course taught by H. Blumer.
  - Research Materials (Box 14)
  - Freedom and Equality Conference, 1978 (Box 14)
  - Studies and Manuscripts, Cornell, 1965-1966 (Box 14)
    - Corinth Study (Box 14)
    - Burlington Study (Box 14)
    - Labor Union Organizing Campaign (Box 14)
    - Sheffield Campaign (Box 14)
  - Name Guides (Box 14)
    Roy substituted fictional pseudonyms for the names of people he interviewed and places he studied in order to maintain confidentiality. This file includes a key to Roy's name code.
  - Field Notes, 1946-1951 (Box 15)
    - Field Notes, 1948-1951 (Box 15)
      Includes material collected at factories in Chicago and was most likely used for Roy's dissertation.
    - Field Notes, 1946-1948 (Box 16)
  - Clippings (Box 16)
  - Southern Labor History Conference, Atlanta, April 1976 (Box 16)
  - Notes, Pensacola, Fla., Sept. 1961 (Box 16)
  - Field Notes, Aug. 20, 1973-July 31, 1979 (Box 17)
    - Aug. 20-Dec. 23, 1973 (Box 17)
      Includes notes taken in Charlotte, N.C.; Cheraw, S.C. (Wallace Campaign); Roanoke Rapids, N.C.; and Aberdeen, N.C.
    - Jan. 8-Dec. 9, 1974 (Box 17)
      Includes notes taken in Roanoke Rapids, N.C. and Raleigh, N.C. (Hearing on Stevens Campaign, Federal Court House). Also includes notes taken from talks given by P. Gallaudet to a sociology class at UNC-CH, and by J. Coyne to one of Roy's sociology classes at Duke.
    - Jan. 29-Dec. 23, 1975 (Box 18)
      Includes notes taken in Wallace, N.C.; Wilmington, N.C.; Greensboro, N.C.; Roanoke Rapids, N.C.; and Enfield, N.C. Also includes notes taken at talks with McConville; from a letter from P. Swaity about a survey of attitudes of workers to unionization; with Swaity at RDU airport; from questionnaires from Swaity; revisions with Ed. Butler; and with Mr. and Mrs. Briggs at Duke Hospital.
    - Jan. 4-Dec. 5, 1976 (Box 18)
      Includes notes taken in Roanoke Rapids, N.C. and Enfield, N.C. Also includes notes taken at talks with Maurene at Duke Hospital and with J. Kissack
    - Jan. 20-Nov. 20, 1977 (Box 18)
      Includes notes taken in Roanoke Rapids, N.C.; Laurinburg, N.C.; Elkin, N.C.; Wallace/Wilmington, N.C.; Aberdeen, N.C.; Greenville, S.C.; and Spartanburg, S.C. Also includes notes taken at talks with Ulf Damman.
    - Feb. 5-Dec. 19, 1978 (Box 19)
      Includes notes taken in Roanoke Rapids, N.C.; Hillsborough, N.C.; Laurinburg, N.C.; Charlotte, N.C.; and Raleigh, N.C. Also includes notes taken at talks with R. Andrews, J. Andrews, and Chesenhall.
    - Jan. 2-July 31, 1979 (Box 19)
      Includes notes taken in Roanoke Rapids, N.C.; Greenville, N.C.; Laurinburg, N.C.; Charlotte, N.C.; and Wagram, N.C. Also includes notes taken at talks with U. Damman, Zivalich, P. McCullough, and Och-ja (Korea).